A Guide to the Sam Granick papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA232
Rockefeller Archive Center
Sam Granick papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1934-1978
Rockefeller Archive Center
Granick, Sam
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA232
7.48 Cubic Feet Extent is an approximation
Biographical/Historical note
Sam Granick, 1909-1977. Biological chemist and plant pathologist.
Born in New York City on February 16, 1909, Granick received his B.S. degree in 1931, M.S. in 1933, and Ph. D. in 1936 in plant physiology from the University of Michigan, where he was a Newcombe Fellow from 1932 to 1936. He spent the next two years at the University of Michigan as a teaching assistant and then an instructor, before joining the staff of the RIMR as a Visiting Investigator in 1938. In 1939, Granick was appointed a Fellow and worked in the laboratory of Leonor Michaelis. He was made an assistant two years later, became an associate professor in 1951, and a professor in 1964.
For more than thirty years, Granick's research interests were in the areas of chloroplast structure, heme and chlorophyll biosynthesis, and iron metabolism. His separation of chloroplasts from the plant cell was one of the earliest examples of the isolation of a cell organelle and made possible for the first time quantitative determinations of their composition. In 1947, he and Dr. Keith R. Porter took the first electron microscope pictures of the chloroplast, which revealed their dense grana and disc-like components.
With Dr. Aharon Gibor, Dr. Granick found earliest evidence for the self-replication of DNA in chloroplasts by irradiation of the cytoplasm. He also discovered that the pigments of protoplasm, heme and chlorophyll, were members of the same biosynthetic chain.
Granick's first research interest at the RIMR was the iron-protein, ferritin, which he studied in connection with its magnetic properties. He helped in the discovery of a new protein, apoferritin, which acts as a storage depot in the human body to form hemoglobin, the red color substance in the blood.
Sam Granick died of a heart attack at New York Hospital on April 29, 1977.
Member of National Academy of Sciences, Member; American Chemical Society; American Academy of Arts and Sciences; American Society of Biological Chemists; American Society of Plant Physiologists; Botanical Society of America; Society for Developmental Biology; Harvey Lecturer; Phi Beta Kappa; Sigma Xi; Phi Kappa Phi; Junior Research Club of the University of Michigan.
Served as a referee for various journals and NIH and NSF grant proposals.
Was married to Dr. Elsa Bachman and had two children, Joel Lee and Donna.
Arrangement note
Arranged in alphabetical and chronological order.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 G766
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Blood; Hemoglobin; DNA; Proteins; Life sciences; Plant cells and tissues; Biochemistry; Medical sciences; Medical technology; Medical education; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Biology -- Research; Medical research; Science -- Study and teaching; Granick, Sam; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University
- Biographical Material, 1950-1977, undated; 1; 1 folder
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes bibliographies, biographies, clippings, curriculum vitae, memos, and obituaries.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Biographical Material, 1950-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1937-1977; 2; 1.4 Cubic Feet
  - Administrative, 1937-1977; a; 0.2 Cubic Feet
    Subjects include the hiring of Granick and the hiring of personnel for Granick's laboratory.
    - 1937-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1954-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General, 1948-1963 1967-1977; b; 1.2 Cubic Feet
    Also includes memos.
    Correspondents include: William Agosta, Edward H. Ahrens, E.C. Albritton, Robert A. Aldrich, American Chemical Society, E.G. Anderson, Richmond K. Anderson, Reginald M. Archibald, W.O. Baker, S.I. Beale, Alexander G. Beam, Martin L. Black, Matthew Block, Lawrence Bogorad, James Bonner, Armin C. Braun, Frank Brink, Detlev W. Bronk, Bruce T. Burnham, George E. Cartwright, Britton Chance, Merrill W. Chase, Frank F.H. Cheng, J. Julian Chisholm, Frank A. Clarke, Bayard D. Clarkson, Seymour Cohen, Waldo Cohn, Aristine Coker, H. Bruce Collier, Alsoph H. Corwin, Lyman C. Craig, James F. Crow, Howard J. Curtis, Harrison Davies, Robert A.M.C. DeGroote, F. DeMatteis, Manfred Doss, Lennox Eales, John T. Edsall, A.M. Edwards, Matthew Ellenhorn, W.H. Elliott, Herman T. Epstein, John E. Falk, Myron W. Fisher, Waldo R. Flinn, Karl Folkers, Beverly W. Gabrio, Hans Gaffron, Arthur W. Galston, Martin A. Garstens, Herbert S. Gasser, Martin Gibbs, Aharon Gibor, Theodore Gillman, David M. Greenberg, Alexander B. Gutman, Philip Handler, Pauline M. Harrison, Felix Haurowitz, Sterling B. Hendricks, Harry R. Highkin, Rollin D. Hotchkiss, F.E. Hull, Arthur A. Iodice, Herbert Jaffe, Martin D. Kamen, Attallah Kappas, Joan Keilin, Albert Kelner, Chin Dong Kim, William R. Kinkel, Heinrich Kluver, Moses Kunitz, Henry G. Kunkel, Donald W. Kupke, Daniel N. Lapedes, Earl G. Larsen, June Lascelles, Richard Levere, L.M. Long, Evelyn McCune, S. Fergus MacDonald, William D. McElroy, David Mauzerall, Leonor Michaelis, Alfred Mirsky, Carl V. Moore, Ursula Muller-Eberhard, Ken Nadler, National Academy of Sciences, National Institutes of Health, National Science Foundation, J.B. Neilands,? Nicholas, Robert Omata, George Palade, S. William Pelletier, Philip Person, John W. Porter, C. Rimington, Thomas Rivers, M.N. Runner, Elizabeth S. Russell, Ruth Sager, Anthony S. San Pietro, Seiyo Sano, Shigeru Sassa, P. Schaeffer, Rudi Schraid, Eugene M. Schryner, Samuel Schwartz, William Seifriz, Frederick Seitz, David Shemin, Peter Sinclair, James H.C. Smith, Fabio Sparatore, Herbert Stern, George S. Strassman, William R. Taylor, William Trager, Bernard F. Trum, William J. Turner, Donald D. Van Slyke, Gilbert J. Vosburgh, Andy Wang, Cecil J. Watson, D.J. Weatherall, A. Weissberger, Diter von Wettstein, Douglas M. Whitaker, David C. White, Torben K. With, and Yoshio Yoshida.
    Subjects include comments by Granick on others publications, letters of recommendation, reports on experiments, and routine correspondence, including requests for chemicals.
    Arranged in alphabetical order by correspondents' last name and then in chronological order.
    - A-AO (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - AP-AZ (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - B-BOE (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - BOGORAD, LAWRENCE (1950-1972) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - BOL-BZ (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - C-COR (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - COT-CZ (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - D (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - E (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - F (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - G-GL (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - GO-GZ (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - H (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - I (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - J (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - K (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - L (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - M-MA (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - ME-MZ (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - N (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - O (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - P (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - R (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - S-SCHM (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - SCHO-SMI (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - SMO-SZ (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - T (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - U (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - V (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - W-WH (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - WI-WZ (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - X, Y, Z & Unidentified (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Permission requests, 1954; c; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Scope and Contents
    Permissions requested by Granick to use others' material in his publications
- Laboratory Notebooks, 1942-1977; 3; 4.5 Cubic Feet Extent is an approximation.
  Includes graphs and notes; also includes articles, charts, correspondence, photographs, reports, and slides.
  Arranged in chronological order and then in alphabetical order.
  NOTE. All of the folders have maintained their original title, insofar as it was possible to read Granick's handwriting. Also, there appeared to be two groups of lab notebooks - those arranged chronologically (with titles in some cases) and those arranged by title of the experiments being performed. This arrangement has been kept.
  - 1942 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Globin Prophyrins, 11/1/1944-3/3/1945 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Chlorella Chloroplasts, Electron Microscope, I, 12/17/1945-2/27/1947 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Chlorella Chloroplasts, Electron Microscope, II, 12/17/1945-2/27/1947 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Agglutin Serum in Porphyrins in Tissue, Heme Chrome Toxins, 1945 1948 1949 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Chlorella Media Anaerobic Studies, Parainfluenza, Prodigious, I, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chlorella Media Anaerobic Studies, Parainfluenza, Prodigious, II, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Chlorella, 11/26/1948-7/3/1951 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Experiments with Index, 10/1948-1/1951 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Horseheart Cytachromes, I, 9/13/1949-2/2/1950 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Horseheart Cytachromes, II, 9/13/1949-2/2/1950 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Prophyrin A, 1/23/1951-1953 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Chlorella, 1951 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Radio Fe, I, 9/24/1953-4/22/1954 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Radio Fe, II, 9/24/1953-4/22/1954 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Radio Tracer Methods & Expts, 10/1950 12/10/1953-3/29/1954 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Protoporphyrin Synthesis in RBC, I, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Protoporphyrin Synthesis in RBC, II, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Coproporphyrin from Diphtheria; Starch Electrophoresp of Electrophoresis Convection, I RBC Hemoysates, 2/25/1954-5/8/1956 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Coproporphyrin from Diphtheria; Starch Electrophoresp of RBC Hemoysates, Electrophoresis Convection, II, 2/25/1954-5/8/1956 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Enzyme, 1954-1956 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Euglena Coprogen, 9/24/1956-7/10/1958 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Chlorophyll, I, 11/29/1958-4/8/1959 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Chlorophyll, II, 11/29/1958-4/8/1959 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Barley & Beans, 9/22/1959-10/1960 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Microscope Studies, 1/4/1960-10/14/1960 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - H3, D2, 1/5/1960-9/14/1961 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Mg Proto, 3/17/1961-6/14/1961 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 12/18/1961-5/1/1962 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Embryo Chick Liver, Induction dAL Synth, I, 9/1962-4/1963 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Embryo Chick Liver, Induction dAL Synth, II, 9/1962-4/1963 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 11/20/1963-7/1/1964 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - I, 12/1963-1/1965 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - II, 12/1963-1/1965 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 10/14/1964-1/13/1965 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - I, 1/20/1965-6/8/1965 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - II, 1/20/1965-6/8/1965 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 1/18/1966-5/24/1966 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 6/1966-9/1966 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 9/1966-2/1967 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 12/1967-6/1969 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Muscle, 4/1968-10/1968 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Muscle, 10/1968-11/3/1969 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Proto Chlorophyllide-Light Reactions, I, 1/17/1969-2/3/1969 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Proto Chlorophyllide-Light Reactions, II, 1/17/1969-2/3/1969 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - 8/1969-6/1970 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 8/1970-5/17/1971 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - 2/1971-9/1971 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - 5/20/1971-7/26/1971 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - ALA Method, I, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - ALA Method, II, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 7/1971-12/23/1972 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - ALA-S, 8/1972 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Antibody Synth, ALA-Pyrrole, 8/1972 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Porphyrins in Blood - Lead Poisoning, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - 12/27/1972-4/18/1973 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Insulin, I, 4/23/1973-6/30/1973 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Insulin, II, 4/23/1973-6/30/1973 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - 7/9/1973-2/12/1974 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - I, 5/1/1974 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - LI, 5/1/1974 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Mice, 6/4/1975 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - I, 11/10/1976-2/9/1977 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - II, 11/10/1976-2/9/1977 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - 2/17/1977 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Lab. Methods, 1973-1974 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Literature Analyses. Heme. Porphyrins. Bile Pigments, 1940s (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Memos & Notes I, 1976-1977 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Memos & Motes II, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Memos & Notes III, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Memos Notes IV, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Memos & Notes V, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Memos & Notes VI, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - NaBH4. Glutaldehyde..., I, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - NaBH4. Glutaldehyde..., II, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Pyrroles. Bile Pigment Methods. Test Literature, 1940s (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - TLC, Fe Proto Prep & Expts, 2/10/1977 (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Manuscripts, 1957-1958; 4; 1 folder
  Notes and reports.
  Subjects include Granick's annual report - handwritten and typed - for 1957-1958.
  - Manuscripts, 1957-1958 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1939-1973, undated; 5
  Includes electron micrographs, laboratory shots, and portraits.
  Subjects include Granick and tobacco chloroplasts.
  Arranged in chronological and in alphabetical order.
  - Electron Micrographs, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Electron Micrographs, Record Sheets, 1952 1957 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Electron Micrographs, RCA 1A, 5/30/1957 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Electron Micrographs, RCA 1B, 5/30/1957 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Electron Micrographs, RCA 3B, 5/30/1957 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Electron Micrographs, RCA 4B, 5/30/1957 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Electron Micrographs, RCA 5A, 5/30/1957 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Electron Micrographs, Siemens 5, 5/30/1957 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Electron Micrographs, Siemens 6, 5/30/1957 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Electron Micrographs, Siemens 7, 5/30/1957 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Electron Micrographs, Tobacco Chloroplast, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Glass Negatives, 1957 May 30 (Box 16)
  - Mounted Prints - Chromonas, 1952 May 12; package 1 (Package 1)
  - Mounted Prints - Siemens 6, 7, 1957 May 30; package 1 (Package 1)
- Reprints, 1934-1978; 6; 3 folders & 8 volumes
  Includes reprints; also includes a booklet and reports by Granick on papers by others.
  - Reprints (#157-159), 1977-1978 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Reprints - NAS Biographical Memoir of L. Michaelis, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Reprints - Reports by SG on Papers by Others, 1950-1951 (Box 15, Folder 18)